hi everyone it's awesome to be back here
was here in 2010 two years ago lots
changed since then I'm actually gonna
put this on the ground this is my timer
you see part of being a founder of a
company is solving your own problems so
I was thinking about this talk and what
I would talk about what what the big
questions would be for me about github
where we've been where we're going what
does it mean to to start a company today
and I figured most of you and especially
after watching Ben's talk might be
asking how do I as a budding
entrepreneur raise a hundred million
dollars just like github did maybe
that's the question that you're that
you're wondering pretty much anywhere I
go now everyone says hey Tom how's it
going what are you gonna spend a hundred
million dollars on but this I think is
the wrong question I'm not actually
going to tell you how to do that I'm
gonna tell you something different and I
think that's because at the end of the
day money isn't actually what matters
money is irrelevant what is money money
is just a number in some banks computer
that says how many slides you can buy
for your office right but that's not
what we care about that's not what we're
trying to do here we're not trying to
just make more slides happen in the
world so what does matter I think what
matters is not the money it's other
things so let's let's think about this I
forgot my clicker I need my clicker this
is gonna be less impactful if I don't
have my my thing okay thank you sir all
right you guys are in for a treat okay
now that I have this okay so let me let
me let me make a positive something for
you guys a company is nothing except the
decisions that it makes
decisions are made by people okay with
me so far
so the only thing that matters our
people people are the only thing that
matters and those people then had better
be the right people so let me tell you
about github in the very early days
github was started by myself and my
co-founder chris wanstrath initially
there was two of us what I did was the
design the front-end the very the just
the visual and the UX I also did the
very back end which is how rails code
accesses git repositories on disk so I'm
kind of this weird creature and then I
do the front-end stuff and I do the
backend stuff but I've been doing rails
for a long time before that and I didn't
really like it I really like rails you
can tell the world I don't actually like
rails that much and so I was you know in
being in the Ruby community and going to
Ruby meetups this is how I found my
co-founders and chris wanstrath was very
big into rails he had a blog post that
outlined everything about how to be the
best rails developer you can be
everything about it was amazing I said
this is a guy that I can start a company
with because we have complementary
skills I'll do the front and back end
he'll do the middle part and together we
have the whole thing and that worked out
really well we just started hacking on
it on a side side project but then
shortly thereafter and here's here's a
little tidbit about how can you tell
whether your startup idea is actually
gaining traction how is it how do you
how can you tell if people enjoy it one
thing that was really effective for us
was when people came to us this is in
the private beta phase and they asked
can I pay for this we had no billing
system and yet they wanted to pay for it
they wanted to make sure that it would
continue to exist so that it would
continue to solve their problems so if
you have customers asking you to pay for
your company's product before you can
even sell it to them that's a good sign
so in order to a come
in order to get this company to a place
where people could actually buy it we
hired our third co-founder he came on
board it was just a few months after we
had started and he as his first thing
built the billing system this is PJ
Hyatt so now he had two rails guys
essentially and me still doing front and
back-end we're building out a better mix
of people and skills to accomplish what
we need to get done our first employee
that we hired name's Scott Chacon he is
a git expert so we reached a level in
the company where we kind of maxed out
our git knowledge none of us would
really get experts and yet we're
building this site github which is for
hosting git repositories so again
through meetups we met Scott we talked
to him we talked to him about product
about how he would go about building
things and he was the one that built
gist which is the snippet sharing site
he built that from scratch as his first
task bringing his get knowledge into the
equation and so you can see we're
assembling a broader diversity of people
who can accomplish more things we max
out our get knowledge let's bring
someone in that can augment that and
you'll notice that none of these people
none of the four of us were business
people none of us had ever really gone
into business all that much I'd done
some consulting but that doesn't really
count none of us had created large
businesses none of us had an MBA
background or a business background like
that so none of us either were
executives none of us had this really
broad experience in creating a company
that you might as a person starting out
think well how are we gonna solve this
problem well let's let's hire an
executive because they know what they're
doing now you have two problems
here's the thing no you know there are
executives and they're awesome great
people but they know so much they know
so much that it can be detrimental I
think to a start-up where you're really
trying to solve a new problem in a
different way you have to come to
problems with beginner's mind right not
knowing something can be a very powerful
tool in to accomplishing it because you
don't know that it's not possible that's
what doing a start-up is not realizing
that something is impossible in doing it
anyway something else that was a
commonality between us the people in
github in the earliest days was having
worked for bad companies before having
worked in places where they did things
wrong examples of how not to do
something are just as good as examples
of how to do something and I think this
is what companies are for companies
solve problems great companies solve
real problems and if you haven't ever
experienced problems then how can you
know what are the right ones to solve so
you're all here to do startups to join
startups to create startups I think that
if your options are creative startup or
try so you know go work for another
company going and working for other
companies is not so bad because it gives
you this really excellent perspective on
things to not do actually so getting
experience elsewhere not so bad right a
lot of great people that start startups
had a bunch of full time jobs before
that I had five I had five full time
jobs before starting github so suffering
can sometimes lead to a better product
for having that information
something that's that's great with
people is getting together we would meet
for beers all the time and we talk over
the problems that we had we go to a bar
called O'Reilly up in North Beach San
Francisco and we just talked through the
big problems right people are very
important having the same ideas for the
product direction is important getting
on the same page for that stuff is
what's gonna allow you to push forward
if you find yourself in a situation
where you're not getting along with your
co-founders or the very small team that
you've created to begin with really step
back and evaluate that problem because I
don't think you can push forward
effectively if you're fighting each
other right look at that you should be
getting along if you're not really
really think about what that means
hiring is hard hiring the right people
is incredibly hard sometimes you'll
screw it up
we hired a sales person in the very
early days and we had to let him go
because he wasn't the culture fit it was
because we hadn't had experience with
that kind of hiring before and that's
okay you're gonna screw up hiring you
have to be in a place mentally where you
can fix that later on by letting someone
go it sucks
firing people is the worst but if you're
gonna start a company you have to be the
kind of person that can do that when it
needs to get done and as your company
matures and you go through these
different phases things are gonna change
your role is going to drastically change
over time in the beginning I described
myself as the janitor I was fixing
things things always need to be fixed I
was always cleaning things up and fixing
things documenting things things are
going so fast that someone has to come
back kind of fix things up every once in
a while I was the janitor and this I
think is why titles are
especially in the beginning of a company
just throw all your titles away don't
even worry about it don't bicker about
who's gonna be the CEO or the CTO or the
CFO all that stuff is crap all that
stuff is crap in the beginning there's
way too much to be done to specialize
that early on things change a little bit
when you get bigger you start to
specialize a little bit more and then
it's really important to think from the
early days do you have the right mix of
personality types
so for us I if I look at the different
people who are in the company in the
early days and why we've been able to
stay together as a team all four of us
are still there today five years later
I'm sort of the logical pragmatic one of
the group Chris is more of the product
visionary one PJ is kind of a business
operations minded person and Scott
guards the culture and creates as much
happiness as possible these are four
sort of different vectors and in having
a discussion and all are just all our
decisions we would make by sitting down
over beers and coming to a conclusion
that was sort of in the middle we would
all check and balance each other so
think about when you're collecting the
right people do they have the right kind
of mix to be effective in the long term
because that's what you're going for so
always think about how every person can
effectively push the company forward if
you're gonna hire someone how are they
gonna push the company forward because
companies don't do things people do
things and that's why people are all
that matters and so I'm gonna have the
audience help me for this real quick I
want everyone from here over to on the
count of three so one two three and then
go read this off and say people are the
only thing that matters okay are you
ready one two three people are the only
thing that matters thank you you're an
excellent audience but wait customers
don't interact with people not when
you're building a product so how can
they be the most important thing product
is actually the only thing that matters
ah things are getting interesting I
think when you're thinking about your
product you need to start with design
it's how your customers interact with
your products it's what they see it's
what they feel think of it like an
automobile
we all understand cars and trucks and
things right this is your this is your
experience this is what you're creating
you're creating something that is like a
vehicle vehicles to us make a lot of
sense
they've been refined year over year for
a large part of the last century so they
become very good we all understand them
this is what you're going for a product
that feels so natural that it's like a
car you can just get in you can drive it
off the steering wheels here this pedal
makes you go and this motor pedal makes
you stop that's the product and what you
exclude from your product is just as
important as what you include in your
product take for instance Volkswagen the
bug that had the little flower vase
right what the hell was that now every
time you get in your car it smells like
dead organic matter and you wonder if
Volkswagen the company is is just the
same thing is this dying company that's
including these crazy things into their
product what you what you leave out is
just as important everything that you
add makes everything else less important
so if you've got your your awesome car
right and and you put that big spoiler
on the back then your neon ground
effects aren't gonna be is awesome
because people are distracted by the
spoiler so think about that everything
that you add dilutes the entire product
our designer our first dedicated
designer that we hired Kyle Neath has a
very nice way of putting this he says
focus over features and I think that's a
very important thing to remember
especially when you're early you can't
do everything so the things that you do
had better be awesome they better be the
right things and
dilute it by just tacking on every
possible thing that you can think of
thinking that users want just as many
features as possible people want great
products not as many features as they
want if you screw up your design then
you screw up your product so make sure
that one of your co-founders is design
minded for us it was me if you're gonna
do a start-up and you're thinking about
okay I'm a technical guy and I'll you
know I'll hire my technical friends and
we'll start a company together now you
need a designer go find a designer
someone who's gonna make your product
something that customers want to use
instead of stuff like the administrative
screens of open source projects that we
see today this is a big problem with
open source is that there's not a lot of
designers involved that's not what you
want your company to be like another
thing is to think very much about your
mission what is the mission of your
company and I think that you should be
able to say your mission in one sentence
and in fact probably in less than ten
words so for us when github started our
mission was very simple in fact it was
on the website some of you might
remember it said get hosting no longer a
pain in the ass because that was the
core problem that we were trying to
solve make get hosting really easy so
you can share code with your friends it
was a very simple mission over time once
we got further down the road of
accomplishing that we started thinking
more about developers as a whole what do
they need to do to be effective at
creating software it's more than just
getting repositories online now it's
about collaboration it's about them
working together and so we changed our
mission we stated it as make developers
lives better every day so we expanded
the scope of what we were trying to
solve then we started building internal
tools for ourselves things that are
beneficial to creating a software
business and we started thinking about
things a little bit differently still so
we're going broader we started saying we
use github to build github because it's
more products than just github calm
things like some things that you have
seen like the job's site jobs at
github.com
things like just a bigger suite of
products that can help you solve more
problems and now the final vision that
we have now is what we call making it
easier to work together than to work
alone you'll see that it's completely
divorced from software altogether and so
I will actually answer your question
what are we gonna do with the hundred
million dollars it's that how many
people in the world use code how many
people in the world write code thirty
million maybe forty if you're lucky how
many people are there in the world
there's a lot more room to fix
collaboration than just software but
this took a long time to get to we
didn't start with this idea of fixing
collaboration for the world we started
with the idea of getting a repository
from your computer onto the internet
that was it so remember that when you're
solving a problem pick something that
you can solve hopefully there's a
direction that you can go that becomes
bigger right but choose something small
in the beginning that you can actually
solve if you bootstrap like we did and
your product becomes popular then you'll
also be faced with a choice which is are
we going to do this as a lifestyle
business is our product going to be a
lifestyle very niche kind of thing and
yet it'll make your life really your
lives really good you can live with that
with that way that's awesome lots of
people do this that's great but you'll
also be faced with the choice which is
do we want to blow this out we want to
change the world if people like your
product you've got a bunch of users
that's a choice that you will have to
make I like to think about it like the
TV show Lost how many of you have seen
that show lots of you have seen that
show yes I think the saddest thing in
the world is a squandered opportunity
and that's what lost was
so that's the question when you're faced
with that choice think about what do you
want to do with your life what are we
trying to accomplish I think you're all
here today to solve big problems so
maybe you've already made that choice
but you might have to make it for real
down the road don't squander an
opportunity go for it
don't be like lost for us it was the
decision to reinvest everything that we
made in the company into the company
instead of banking it out putting in our
bank accounts this is also why we raised
a hundred million dollars because github
is an opportunity we don't want to
squander it don't worry too much about
when you enter a market almost every
product in the world is terrible look at
the list of products the things that use
it every day most of them are just
downright crap if you know this and this
is something that Apple knows very well
with devices like the iPad right how
many tablet computers were there before
the iPad dozens all terrible Apple comes
along and through making a good product
day one
that's what product means and that is
why product is all the matters so you
center section on a count of three
please help me in saying this phrase one
two three product is all the matters but
wait
products only come into being when
people make decisions like we started
with and the best decisions are made
according to a consistent philosophy so
philosophy is all that matters
philosophy derives from your people at
github we never set out to create a
specific culture the people that we
hired created the culture at some point
you might want to codify this culture
that is inherently created through the
people that you hire so that you can
communicate it well let me briefly
explain what to me the five core values
of github are number one optimizing for
happiness if you want to learn more
about that watch my talk from two years
ago optimizing for happiness means think
about what you're doing and how it's
going to create more happiness in the
world for your customers for your team
members and for your shareholders if you
do options like most startups do then
your team members are also your
shareholders if you raise money then
your shareholders are part of that
equation as well if you do those things
if you optimize for happiness my theory
is that profits will result naturally
and it puts you on the right path to do
things that matter
number two best argument wins this means
that it's not about ego it's not about
who you are where you came from it's
about making good arguments backing them
up and being open to other people's
arguments this is critical to avoiding
politics within a company if you can
argue about something that matters and
the argument is the thing and not the
people behind it then you can have good
results you can create good product and
you can avoid politics number three
working from first principles everything
that we do we do from scratch you might
think this is very inefficient sometimes
it is
but we think through every problem that
way because github is a unique company
just like every company is unique you
can't just take the ideas that work for
some other company and apply them to
yourself and in fact you can't take the
ideas that I give you today or that
anyone gives you today and just copy
them and expect them to work for you you
have to think about what it means for
your company this is how you create
something new something better number
four create superfans
Travis's talk about uber and how they
delight their users on certain holidays
giving them a motorcade that's the kind
of stuff that I'm talking about for us
we do drink ups it's like a meetup
accepted to the bar and we buy you beer
for developers this turns out to be
incredibly effective that's just one of
many things how we deal with support
what I love about our support team is
that we measure our success the success
of a support interaction by Counting how
many explode exclamation points are in
the response from an end user that's
creating superfans creating that kind of
experience that goes above and beyond
what is expected and number five be
awesome and change the world that one's
pretty self-explanatory so if you have a
strong culture you can use it as a
hiring tool it's amazingly effective and
this is really critical today as it
becomes more and more difficult to hire
as all of you who would normally be
entering the workforce are instead
starting your own companies the pool of
candidates is smaller the competition is
higher since the early days of github
we've evangelized our way of working our
culture and our values and the
philosophy that gives us that higher
purpose all of this allows you to
attract the kind of people that
naturally fit your philosophy and so
those people that you're attracting
through this communication will make the
right kinds of decisions
and since decisions are how make people
make products the philosophy that guides
those decisions is all that matters
so please third segment of the audience
on three one two three philosophy is all
that matters I'm not convinced that you
believe it but okay so I've told you
three things that are the only things
that matter how can that possibly be
which of these things three things is
the only thing that matters I don't
think I have to answer that question I
think it's a false trichotomy someone
really enjoyed that joke
thank you hold on I'm not done yet hold
on hold on hold hold on I'm not just
gonna end on false dichotomy okay
in reality in reality just like the
three quarks of an atom cannot exist on
their own people product and philosophy
are also inseparable so do you guys
remember what was the only thing that
mattered people do you guys remember the
only thing that mattered product do you
guys remember the only thing that
mattered philosophy on three everybody
say what you said before together one
two three if you master these things
then you will finally have the answer to
the question how do I raise 100 million
dollars
thank you